There's been a lot of drama on Twitter
today around Tailwind. And if I'm being
honest, the word drama doesn't really do
it justice. This has nothing to do with
the usual debates around Tailwind, like,
"Oh, you're going to make your markup so
ugly." Yeah, because it's the best way
to do CSS. We've established this for a
long time now. Watch any of my other
videos. I don't want to talk about
whether or not Tailwind is good today.
Because whether or not you agree with
Tailwind being good, there's a reason it
is so popular. And that reason is
probably because it's pretty good. But
that's not what today is about. This is
what today is about. Specifically, 75%
of the engineering team for Tailwind
just lost their jobs. This is not good.
Whether or not you like Tailwind has
nothing to do with the harsh reality
that we're seeing here. This is one of
the first examples of AI immediately
causing engineers to lose jobs. Not like
laid off based on speculation, but
actual revenue going down for a business
because of AI and the results being
people losing their jobs. The Tailwind
org's revenue is down 80%. That's 80% of
the money they were making, which was
enough to mostly survive gone. And AI is
a huge part of that. This sucks. This
sucks so bad that on a day that I was
planning on taking off because I have
the flu. Like, I'm sorry for my voice
being so congested, but I want to take
the time to talk about this cuz we
haven't seen anything like it before.
And I have a bad feeling we're about to
start seeing a lot more of it. Normally,
I would make some joke about how I don't
want to go broke, so I'm going to do a
sponsor spot, but that no, not today.
This is this is just sad. So, yeah, I do
have to roll an ad here, but we'll we'll
do something to make up for that in just
a bit. Do you know what OpenAI, Cursor,
Foul, Snowflake, Carta, T3 Chat, and
more all have in common. It's that
they're all in this list. But, uh, what
is this list? This company's using work
OS. Yes, all of those brands, including
my own, decided that rolling our own off
wasn't the best call. I made this
mistake with T3 chat and it cost us
potential enterprise contracts because,
well, we didn't have any way to
authenticate those users. And you're
probably dealing with this, too. If you
had Microsoft show up to your office
today saying, "Hey, we want to sign a
contract for a thousand accounts. How do
we set up our bespoke weird O to work
with your service?" Are you ready to
handle that? Probably not. But if you
start today with work OS, you will be.
The admin portal is incredible. You
literally just send a link to the
company that you're working with. They
pick whatever identity provider they use
and now they can have their employees a
to your service without you having to do
anything at all. It's miraculous. And
setting this up yourself is hellish.
Trust me on that one, guys. By the way,
first million users are free. So what do
you have to lose? Check them out now at
soyv.v.link/workos.
This all came to light earlier today
when Adam posted this recording of his
morning walk, just talking to his phone,
recording it, and publishing it. And
there are a lot of painful realizations
in this. And as a fellow founder who's
also had to lay off the majority of
their team in the past, th this one
tugged at the heartstrings. I don't know
if you all know this, but early in 2023
when I realized that doing video product
wasn't really a way to make money, I had
to lay off the almost entirety of the
team at Ping, leaving just Mark and me.
That was six people whose jobs just kind
of vanished and it felt awful. I chose
to do it then cuz I wanted to make sure
I had enough money to give generous
severance and help out with the rest of
the team getting new gigs. And I did my
best there and I'm proud of what we did.
But at the same time, it was probably
the single greatest failure of my career
to even end up in that position. And it
still haunts me to this day. So, I have
so much empathy for the position Adam is
in here and the realization that he had.
The link for this is in the description
if you want to hear the whole thing.
About 33 minutes long. The quick summary
I'll give you is that they saw revenue
going down, but they did the thing all
founders do, which is they kind of
ignore the numbers when they aren't good
until they went back and looked and
realized, "Oh we have 6 months
until we go out of business." and he
decided to do the right thing here,
which is lay people off now so they can
get sufference and go find new jobs
instead of waiting till they were
entirely out of money and now people
just suddenly don't have a job the next
day. Massive respect for Adam for having
this realization and doing this and I
don't have any ill will for him taking
this long to do it. It is incredibly
common. I've invested in enough
companies early stage to know this. No
ill will towards Adam. But we do need to
talk about how we ended up here and what
the future for open source projects like
what they built with Tailwind is going
to be. Before we go to this next
section, I just want to ask you a
question. How does Tailwind make money?
If you're deep enough in the CSS world
and have been around for a long time,
you probably know the answer. But if
you're new here, or maybe you just
started using Tailwind cuz your AI
recommended it, you might not. Well, if
we go to the Tailwind docs, we can find
it relatively quick. Let's just look at
some things here. I don't know. Let's
hop to columns. anything in here? No.
You honestly are gonna have to look
pretty hard. The first thing's obviously
sponsors. Shout out sponsors. We have a
lot of sponsor overlap here. And by the
way, any of my sponsors who are seeing
this, you should consider sponsoring
Tailwind. They could use it. I've
already started pinging a handful of
them that they should be throwing some
money to Tailwind. We're all using it
for all of our stuff. I'm pretty sure at
least 80% of my sponsors are using
Tailwind for at the very least their
like homepages. More of us need to be
supporting and putting money back in.
But now when we scroll far enough, we
see the thing that they charge for,
Tailwind Plus. It's a set of templates,
UI blocks, and a whole UI kit for using
Tailwind. And these are really good sets
of stuff. I was a subscriber of the
original I forgot what it was called
before Tailwind Plus, but they had this
like Tailwind kit thing that you could
buy a long time ago, and it was a $200
lifetime purchase for my business, and
we still use it for a bunch of to
this day. The upload thing docs are
stunning and a huge part of why they are
so stunning is because we used the
Tailwind template for it. It was a
Tailwind next.js template for doing docs
and it was really good. The problem is
that it's not open source. Our docs are
source available and a lot of the rest
of the uploading client code is open
source, but we had to put a different
license for this because it's a thing
that they're selling and they should.
It's really good and I'm happy with the
money we spent, but there's a lot of
problems with this model. The first is
just the monetization strategy. Dax had
a really good reply about this that I've
been thinking about since I saw it. It's
likely you already know all of what I'm
about to say, but just in case, our
teams talked a bunch about y'all yada
yada. We saw you similar to musicians.
Go into a hole and work on an album, do
a drop, go on tour for a bit, and that's
where you make the money. Rinse and
repeat. You don't make money streaming.
It's the amount of artists that can make
a living off of the music that they
release being played and paying them is
very, very small. We're talking a few
hundred people. Most musicians make
their money doing other things like
tours and merch and other physical sales
of things and services to make ends
meet. Your audience grows each time, but
you kind of lose all the advantage of
building an internet business. You have
to fight for every single sale, every
single iteration. It doesn't get easier.
Put another way, you missed out on all
the advantages of compounding. A
customer that you grabbed 5 years ago
should still be paying you. This is the
key. I paid Tailwind that $200 very
excitedly all the way back in 2021, and
I'm still using that lifetime purchase
that I made to get all sorts of useful
things for the stuff that we built. That
said, Claude's gotten good enough at
designing with Tailwind that I don't
find myself reaching for that kit of
stuff anymore because I can make things
that look decent without it. There is
something else that they sell that I do
highly recommend checking out. This is
the Refactoring UI book. Saying this
book changed how I think about design is
an understatement. It's one of the best
things I've ever read as a developer,
and it's still helpful today as a
developer that isn't doing the front-end
work themselves as directly now. It
helps me have a language for describing
why things look off and getting them
fixed. I'm thankful I read this as early
as I did. And funny enough, believe it
or not, this book came out before
Tailwind. You don't even need to be a
Tailwind user to have it be useful. This
is just a good design book. And it was
the lessons that Adam and Steve had that
they learned and solidified through the
writing of this book that resulted in
Tailwind happening. The fact that it is
a free open source project for all of us
to use and consume however we want is an
incredible generosity given by them. But
we have to return the favor as an
industry. We need to buy the book. We
need to use Tailwind Plus. We need to
sponsor. We need to support them back.
That's how open source works. And their
decision to try and make a business
around it was always a risk. But that
risk is compounded massively by the
introduction of AI. Historically, open-
source projects only made their money by
finding something to sell alongside it
for the power users of that project.
Something like Reddus, for example,
would sell services to fund the team
while at the same time building the open
source project for others to use. And
the result was that they changed the
license, broke all of the community
trust, caused this very popular fork
Valky to exist, and then eventually
walked it back and rehired the original
creator. That one was a mess. That's an
example of doing it wrong, but they
tried. A better example is something
like Versell where they made Nex.js, a
super popular, powerful front-end
fullstack framework, but it was too hard
to deploy and they started building
tools to fix these shortcomings that we
had as developers and that ended up
building a very successful business that
they've continued iterating and making
cool things from. I still use heavily
and I haven't built anything with Nex.js
in a couple months. I'm almost at a year
now. Tailwind's similar pitch was
selling help with design. Tailwind makes
it way easier to implement the designs,
but it doesn't make it any easier to be
a good designer. It helps you understand
the CSS better. I still firmly believe I
am better at CSS as a result of using
Tailwind, but what they sell is stuff
like this where they are teaching you
how to be a better designer and also
stuff like plus where you can get really
good starting points for the different
things you want to make. This is so
valuable for us as we built ping and
upload thing and pick thing and so many
of our other projects. Many of them
started as originally versions of these
templates and it was absolutely worth
the money for us. That said, this is now
in competition with AI. The fact that AI
models have gotten as good as they have
means that you can make things that are
to most people who aren't great
designers similar quality to what you're
seeing here. And if you're still not
great at design, you haven't read the
refactoring UI book, you're not deep in
the weeds like many of us are, the
designs that you pull out of Claude
Sonnet 45 are going to look more than
good enough for whatever the heck you're
working on. So the need for templates
like this is hitting the floor fast. And
that sucks. There's a reason that they
lost 80% of their sales. It's because
these things were either purchased by
people like me a long time ago and we're
still using the version we purchased
forever ago or we're using AI and don't
need it anymore. This drama came to head
today because of this particular PR that
has been closed on the Tailwind repo.
Adding LLM.ext endpoints support for the
LM optimized docs for Tailwind. This
would allow for AI models to better
understand all of the cool features
Tailwind has and the LM's text would be
generated as a result of the markdown in
their docs. That's really cool. and
would allow for AI agents to be even
better at Tailwind. Most of them are
already pretty good at it because
they're trained on a lot of the data
from it, but they don't know all of the
new features. They don't know about how
to port from Tailwind V3 to V4. It's one
of my favorite tests and all the agents
bomb it. This PR was an attempt to make
it easier for AI to use Tailwind out of
love of Tailwind. And it's kind of
heartbreaking that the person who filed
this PR is getting for it when
their intent was clearly very good. It's
clear what the goal of Quantisor was
here. He wanted to make it so the AI
tools he uses to build can better
understand how Tailwind works so they
can use it more properly. There's a lot
of push back on Adam in the comments
around how more use should mean more
opportunities to monetize, but that's
not true at all. As he says here, I
totally see the value in this feature
and I would like to find a way to add
it, but the reality is that 75% of the
people on our engineering team lost
their jobs here yesterday because of the
brutal impact AI has had on our
business. And every second I spend
trying to do fun-f free things for the
community like this, the second I'm not
spending trying to turn the business
around and make sure the people who are
still here are getting their paychecks
every month. It is worth noting that the
75% number is three people out of their
fourperson team, but it still sucks so
hard. Tailwind is popular enough that
they should comfortably be able to
employ way more than four engineers, but
again, open source doesn't pay the bills
inherently. They are barely making
enough off of sponsors and whatever
little revenue they still get from
Tailwind Plus to survive now that
they've downsized. Traffic to their docs
is down 40% from early 2023. Despite
Tailwind being more popular than ever,
the docs are the only way people find
out about their commercial product, and
without customers, they can't afford to
maintain the framework. He wants to find
a way to offer LM optimized docs that
doesn't make the situation even worse.
Again, they had to lay off 75% of their
team today. Tailwind is growing faster
than it ever has and it's bigger than
it's ever been and our revenue is down
close to 80%. Right now, there's just no
correlation between making Tailwind
easier to use and making development of
the framework more sustainable. He can't
make Tailwind easier to use right now
because if he can't fix the problem of
it making the revenue go down, the
project's going to become unmaintained
abandonware where there is no one left
employed to work on it. I appreciate the
sentiment and a green spirit is just
more complicated than that in reality.
right now. Yeah, this just sucks and I
wish I had more to say. I have a bad
feeling this is the start of a thing
we're going to see a lot more of going
forward. Projects that would previously
have been able to make money doing
things like consulting, doing things
like selling templates, doing things
like paid modules, they're all going to
fall to the wayside of AI. A lot of the
ways that we would monetize our open
source projects are things you can just
do with an agent that you're already
paying for. If you have a cursor
subscription or a cloud subscription,
you can remake most of what their
templates offer to a high enoughish bar
that you might not even think that you
would want them. And that's that's just
bad. And I don't know how to solve this
problem. I know how Bun solved it. They
got bought by one of these labs. I know
how Open Code is solving it. They just
put up a $200 month sub with a sketchy
stripe link that a bunch of people
bought. I don't know how Tailwind solves
this. There's a lot of good commentary
on this one. I want to just go through
some of the things people have said.
Jake from Railway said that Tailwind's
business is massively down due to AI
adoption. Open source needs a new way to
monetize. The old one is disappearing.
Adam and the team need to be paid for
every CPU cycle. Yep. Views, who's the
creator of React Native, prettier,
excal, you know, the drawing app I use
all the time and way more, had the
following to say. He's had a similar
issue with prettier. It's used by
everyone in the industry, but it has
been a struggle to fund proper
maintenance for it. for Excaladraw. He
went the SAS business model which has
been working better. Yeah, I said
earlier I was going to do something
about the sponsorship. I'm going to do
it. If you are a company that is down to
sponsor Tailwind, I highly recommend it.
All of the tiers are on the docs page.
I'm going to support as an individual.
Hiding the screen so I can do this. I am
now a yearly subscriber to the Tailwind
insiders program. I would recommend you
do the same if Tailwind has brought you
joy. And if you work at a company that
uses Tailwind heavily, I would highly
recommend that they consider sponsoring
the project. It is so important that
projects like Tailwind have enough
success to survive as the way that we
all build changes. It's scary to think
AI might take our jobs as full-time
software developers, but in my opinion,
it's much scarier that it might kill
open source projects like Tailwind. So,
please do your part. Buy the book if you
haven't. It's so good. Like this. Just
do it. It's so worth it. And if you're
an engineer lead or somebody with a
budget at the company, buy a copy for
everyone on your team. They all deserve
it. It'll make their designs and their
application building way better. If
you've already done that, check out the
sponsorships as a business or as an
individual. Support the projects you use
and also go through your dependencies.
Look at who else you're relying on as a
business and see how they are doing
funding wise. Now is a time for us as an
industry to talk more about this more
than ever. As these AI companies are
more and more successful and are making
more and more money, there's a very
important opportunity for us to give
back. And if we don't, we might never
see our technology improve again. That's
my biggest fear. Tailwind v4 was an
incredible launch, but if we don't
support projects like Tailwind, there
will be no V5. There will be no new
React. There will be no new Bun. There
will be no new TRPC. There will be no
new any of the things that we talk about
and use and rely on here on the channel
and in the industry as a whole. Support
the open source projects that we build
on top of so that they don't disappear
in the process. Thank you, Adam, and
thank you, Tailwind team, for everything
you guys have done. You've made me a
better developer and made my businesses
more successful, too. I appreciate y'all
immensely. And I hope that we can make
things move forward in a way that is
more beneficial to Tailwind as a
business. I got nothing else on this
one. I'm going to go take some Nightquil
and pass out. Thank you all as always.
Until next time. Peace nerds.